[Music]
all right Microsoft customer success day
Dynamics con
virtual great to be here my name is
Kenny pontan and I'm the principal I'm a
principal um program manager with
Microsoft working with business Central
every single day and my talk today is
about how you can use data to get low
Freaks and go lives and optimize your
Investments with business Central using
Telemetry data so now that's very scary
Telemetry data what is that well the
agenda for today is exactly this what is
telemetry and why should I
care and then the two main topics of
course using data to get low friction
business Central go lives as well as
after go live how do you do more with
business Central for the license you pay
how to to do more with less with
business Central and hopefully after
this session you think hey I want this
what should I tell my administrator to
get me all this nice insights and if you
even stick around to the end of this
session there's going to be a live Q&A
where I will stick around and ask or
answer any questions that you might have
might have on the topic so stay tuned
for that but um let's dive in telemetry
that's a dangerous word but actually
it's not it's just a fancy word for
usage data all there is to it business
Central Telemetry is opt in you don't
have to use it um administrators can set
it up either you um as a tenant
administrator or your partner can do it
and I will show you in the end how easy
it is to
do and the feature itself has been
designed to be
privacy compliant we designed privacy
into this so whatever you are under gdpr
in European union or have any other
privacy laws regulating what you are
allowed to to do telem just conform to
all of that if teley is enabled for a
business Central
environment we meaning business Central
will lock data about the usage what do
users do in business Central errors if
something goes wrong performance where
time is spent we're not going to talk a
lot about performance in this session
and changes who changed what when and
then before we dive into the first demo
the audience for this is actually it's
both end users or I should say maybe the
people at the customer organization who
really care about the business Central
is a success the implementation is a
success so whether I sometimes call you
the project sponsor because you put some
of your
own um of of yourself into this to make
it work and therefore the more we can do
to make this project work for you the
better right and if you're a partner the
same thing applies you want your
customer to be a success you want this
new business Central environment to
shine and be something that customers
users use and
love so let's have the first quick tour
into powerbi to just to visualize some
of the things that you get with business
Central
Telemetry okay so here I am in the
business Central usage app it's an app
like a powerp app that just means that
this is hosted you you install this from
powerbi App Source but it's just a
powerbi report actually it's four
different reports you get a usage report
here I will dive into that a bit more
you get an error report a performance
report and an Administration report that
is probably mostly for
administrators so let's take a look at a
few of the pages in The usage report the
first here is what we call Dow wow mow
but it's just it's just the the L daily
weekly and monthly users of the system
now business Central Telemetry can have
data for multiple environments or a
single environment it doesn't matter for
us so so this report just shows data as
seen from a situation where multiple
environments log telemet you to the same
database it doesn't have to be the case
if you only have one environment that
you have Telemetry for you would just
have only C data for one environment
right so here you can see um your
current daily weekly monthly usage and
you can see that the last time this was
updated was 18th of
February and you can see the the current
Dow wow Mau counts here are as they are
but you can also see the progress of
usage across um dates here you can see
that um especially for for go live that
you you typically during the go live
phase have only a few users and then
when you enroll the rest of the
organization you will have many more
users enrolled to this that also means
that this Dow wow ma report over time
will typically for go live just grow up
to some number and if we're doing it
right and if the partner is doing it
right with an Eep system your M numbers
are likely to be const because it's the
chance of a user actually using business
Central once a at least once a month is
fairly High whatever uh however the the
Dow the daily usage numbers will be
different they will follow a a pattern
where you see a dip during the the
weekends and then for the weekdays you
see active usage and then a dip for the
weekend and so on so that's something
you can see here how people how your
users use the system um over the over
the the day the week and the monthly
numbers the next page here is sessions
so this is showing you what types of
users are logging in and what types of
clients are they using are they using
teams are they using phone or the web
client when do they log in over the day
over the week and uh and over a calendar
whatever this report has been set to
look data so it you can when you install
this I'll show you later you will have
um ability to say I only want data for
seven days or two weeks or whatever you
like so that will be the calendar you
see
here the next report here is clients so
here you would be able to see what
browsers do people use or what clients
like tablet phone desktop and so on
which green size do they use this is
important if you design new
functionality with new apps maybe
pretended extensions together with a
partner that may if you have users with
small screens maybe small laptops you
want to design the user interface in a
different way than if people have wide
screens so you get that information
here um and you get statistics of which
browsers people use maybe that's boring
the next thing is not boring though this
is the locations page here you can see
from where people log into the system
now my meta My Demo data here shows that
people log in from Denmark because I'm
from Denmark uh from the UK and from
India so the map here shows you from
where do people log in and the so that's
the location and the language column you
see here is showing you Which languages
the users prefer in when they set up
their client and there's
also a visualization down here on user
languages where you can see which are
the languages that your users prefer to
to have business Central set up
in so just some we'll go through some of
the other reports here you might say oh
what about the reports and Page views
we'll get there so I just want to show
you a few more things and then go more
deep into the go live part
for the administration report I just
want to show you two
things the first one is a Change Report
so how many times have you not talking
been talking to someone from it and they
say whenever there's something wrong or
changed it's it's always a change in the
system well this is what this report is
for for the IT department or for for the
partner organization to see whatever
happened on either on the environment or
an extension and so on was the
environment updated was an
extension installed and so on so what
happened when is what this report uh
shows all changes happening across all
environments across these
Dimensions the second page I want to
show you here of field changes now
business Central comes with a nice
feature called sensitive field
monitoring sensitive field monitoring
allows the administrator of business
Central to to say I want to track any
change to these fields it could be a
credit card Bank information whatever
and if you do so this is locked to
Telemetry not the data that was changed
because we don't want to log customer
data into Telemetry but who changed it
is here when was it changed and which
which field in which table was has
changed so you can see that directly
here in the admin report on the field
changes okay let's go back to the to the
presentation and dive a little bit in to
the go live part so data driven low
friction business Central go
lives the go live phase has many many
different things that you on the
customer end and the partner on the
partner end need to take care of in this
presentation I I have two main tasks to
discuss the first one is user acceptance
testing does it work as we expect it to
do and the second part is stability
testing can we remove as much friction
as possible before everyone is onboard
it to business
Central
so let's see how this usage report and
error and usage report can be used as a
way to actually see if people will do
user acceptions testing what do they
test so let's go back to the powerbi
report on the usage report and and look
at a a few scenarios here so I will just
go back up here to the usage report and
dive into the first here is Page views
page views is which pages in The Client
uh have been visited by users so you can
you can you can see see the statistics
of these like this is this page of this
type was um was visited by how many
users and how how many times uh it was
it was visited you can see over the day
like when do people visit different
pages and over the week so let's say
that we are in this user acceptance
testing phase and you have set up with
users that everyone need to test things
on Wednesday on and and they did you can
actually see that everyone did test
things on a Wednesday great like so if
you have data you can see that this
confirms what was supposed to happen
there's also a different uh situation
what if they actually didn't test let's
say that the test was scheduled for a
Saturday and everyone went out to play
golf you can see here no one tested the
system on Saturday actually no one did
on Sunday so maybe you need to go back
to the project group and find out what's
going on like when when when are you
going to test the functionality that
that we are supposed to do uh speaking
of that there's actually um even a place
that shows you highlights of the
application this is the base application
which places in the base application
were um touched by users so for instance
here in the finance part um we can see
that no one test it fixed assets item
charges tax vat workflow but there were
people who tested financial reporting
and so on now is this good or bad it
depends if your system does not use
fixed assets well then there's no need
to test it and this absence of data here
is fine but if fixed assets were part of
this implementation plan and test plan
well then you need to go back to the
project group and kind of ask them to
test because they OB obviously didn't
test this part of of the
application reports reports is an
important thing of ANP system to know uh
to have data that guide you to take
decisions in your business so here on
the reports page you can see which
reports have people been running you can
see again uh over the day and over the
week you can see whether they downloaded
previewed print and so on this is
important as well let's say that your
user acceptance testing also included
that you can print well the good thing
for this data is yes they actually did
test Out Printing and you're happy but
uh if there's absence of print here well
no one tried to print an invoice and
maybe you need to make sure that that
works feature usage every single part of
the application in in business Central
as well as if partners who write
applications for for business Central uh
do this um they can instrument everyone
can and a developer can instrument with
what we call feature Telemetry so for
this particular feature this event
happens this many times you can also you
can use this for user exceptions testing
and if Master data management was a key
thing to test well people did actually
do it so that's
good finally for for business
Central um any e system never is just
out there on its own there will always
almost every single Eep system will have
Integrations where people integrate to
read and write data or that that the
apps inside the bu the AP system will
call out to external services and this
is what we call
Integrations okay so here I am on the
Integrations page and here you can see
Integrations to and from business
Central um inside the app published by
Microsoft if you have installed other
apps they will show up here this is
important for your user exceptions
testing because you can also test all
these Integrations to external systems
so this page is should be part of your
user acceptance testing
reporting great let's go back to the
deck and talk about removing friction oh
first I need to tell you of course that
to wrap up the user acceptance
testing what you saw here is you can use
the power Pi report the usage part and
you can simply check if if key Pages
reports features Integrations have been
tested or touched you have data and
there's no need to have status meetings
to ask if people did it you can just see
if they did or if they did
not okay so let's talk about removing
friction the error report and the error
Telemetry is there for that because for
go live you want to make sure that you
get rid of all the annoying low hanging
food errors when you only have few users
on the system so that when you onboard
the rest of the users they have a smooth
experience they don't experience a lot
of Errors let's see how that works uh in
the error report and the error report
comes with a built-in dashboard so here
you have an overview of all the types of
errors that happen in business Central
or can happen you have used errors that
happens where users see errors you have
errors happening to Integrations to
external systems as well as as system
errors like setup errors or anything
that could fail within business Central
so for each of these let's explore a few
of those and uh let's start with
permission errors you actually this is a
great thing to start with with your go
live testing because there would be
permission errors probably many
different places where you don't get set
up of permissions completely right the
first time so let me try to find some
permission error that would be fun here
statistical accounts this is a new
feature by the way coming in version 22
2.0 in the finance so so that's that's
great if you're testing this in user
exceptions testing and apparently
there's something not right with
permissions here so you can see in which
environment it it's it's happening and
then you can go sort that out um as part
of go life so I think that that's that's
a nice first thing to
do the second thing I would do is taking
care of error message feedback so
whenever a user in business Central gets
a use like an error dialogue we added a
voting where they can say was this
helpful yes or no now everyone says if
if they say yes this is a great error
message okay that's fine but everyone
who says Nah this is not good it could
be that you need to provide better
training or maybe go in and tweak the
system so that this error doesn't occur
so for each of these I think maybe we
are lucky that we have here something
about one drive maybe one drive was not
set up for all users so that would be
nice to uh to take care
of the last thing I want to show you for
the error getting errors to zero is
error dialogues whenever a user sees an
error dialogue in the system this is
loged to Telemetry so going back to our
statistical accounts we can uh we can
see that there were 42 errors in that
during our test so it could be that we
needs to go back and see if there's
something that needs to be set up about
statistical accounts or maybe that um
users are using the feature in not the
intended way maybe you need to have more
training maybe the finance department
need to know more about what does this
feature actually do and for the for the
people who maybe need to dive into more
code probably the partner whenever you
click on an error here you can actually
see where it this error is coming from
in which part of the code and who owns
this code this is Microsoft code um and
in in this code unit
here all right so let's recap on our go
live um actually not yet because if you
think of this error dashboard this is
just showing you all the errors that
that is present is stored in Telemetry
right so for go live if you want to
drive these down how do you actually
track progress well you you could take
screenshots of this and every day you
could see if numbers are changing but
that's not right that's not really the
way you want to work as a project
manager project sponsor or a
partner and by the way did I mention
that we do
have a live Q&A after this session so if
anything I talk about if it triggers
some questions just uh write them down
and and we can uh we can get to them in
the end now if you look closely and on
some of the pages in the error report
you notice might have noticed that there
are kpis um called all last seven days
or since
yesterday these kpis are there to track
changes into errors and hopefully you
you can use them these to see let's say
that you set up an initiative during go
live to to drive error job CU errors to
zero then you can see that since
yesterday we actually didn't have any
but we did have 25 over the last 20
seven days so you could go and and kind
of monitor these on each of the pages
but that's not nice as well right you
don't want to go I mean how many pages
in the era report 15 you don't want to
have a daily routine where you every
morning you go in and and you want to
have someone to track this for you right
so with powerbi um this powerbi report
is uh for for you to use that you need a
powerbi pro license that cost you 10
bucks a month $10 US dollars a month for
a license um with that license come also
comes a pretty cool products in my
opinion that is really really good to
track these things for you which is
called powerbi metrics so here in the
powerbi portal there's a there's a goal
there's a something you can win here and
this is uh this is where you create your
first scorecards uh when you create a
scorecard you simply you can give that a
name you can have many scorecards and
then you add metric metric is just a
name for a number over time that's all
there is to it so I created a metric
called daily job Q errors and then for
the for the for this I'm simply
connecting this to the powerp reports
this is where I get my data from and
when I do that I need to select here the
error report and navigate to the job C
errors where I simply pick that number
you just saw there uh on the on the job
C errors and say I want to track the
since yesterday numbers on on job use
every single day and that's what the
metric does it tracks a number uh for
for every day and if you let that simmer
for a few days you can actually see a
progress here of how that number changed
over time
so this shows you this example here that
your your um task force that made daily
like job queue errors go down they
actually succeeded you can see they
drove down from 25 to zero and zero has
been the number for the last 3 days
great now what's even more cool here is
you can set your thresholds of what you
mean by at risk on track and complete it
for each of these metrics and if you do
so and I think this is even more
cool you get all the state changes
directly into teams so this is daily
jump queue errors is now complete
completed so now I get Got a
notification that is simply in teams
that this is now completed but and I
think I really like this this um if if
you set this up during go live and keep
it like that you will even get
notifications if job cure Era start to
climb again and then it would go up in
at risk or even higher right so by
setting this up during go live you have
automatic projects uh surveillance of of
key kpis that you really want to make
sure that these never like degrade or
regress right so for stability testing
for go live just to sum summarize use
the powerbi report for errors and check
your key error scenarios in there and
maybe set up powerbi metrics on these so
that you pro track progress of these
both before during and after go live
right so the next part of this
presentation is how can you do more with
less with business
Central and um I was before I joined
Microsoft part of a consultancy business
and I've been in many many customer
meetings both as a customer and as a A
salesperson what I hate about sales
meetings is people wasting my time what
do I mean about that here are a few
examples these are hypothetical examples
of course your partners would never do
this with
you so are you happy with the new thing
we we made for you right what they're
really saying if I have to be a little
bit rude is I have no idea how you use
the things you paid us to develop not
really a nice way to go into a meeting
right if if the customer thinks this H
maybe we could do better here's another
example did you you know that business
Central now supports that end users make
report layouts with Excel what they're
really saying is I have no idea how you
use business
Central I get I I think you get the
point hey do you use power automate
yet that actually means I have no idea
of if or how you use Power Platform or
Asset Services now as a partner account
manager or actually also as a project
sponsor on the customer end why not use
data to plan new activities together and
if you do have these follow-up meetings
after go live use them to provide value
directly in the meeting instead of
wasting people's lives and time so let's
see a demo of how that could
work I'll shift
over to the usage report again and show
you a few more tricks here so my trick
number one is I just need to look at my
demos here is Excel layouts
so how can we how can we do that so if I
go here to
[Music]
reports and uh I did show you this
report before but I skipped these layout
types um whenever you run a report in
business Central you can either have a
layout of type Excel rdlc is a technical
thing or word right these are the three
different types of reports layouts now
Excel layouts was something we developed
and this Fairly New Concept it's only
been a year in the product with Excel
layouts the end users can layout their
reports with Excel so you simply have a
way to to get your data out in Excel put
pivot tables put put whatever you like
in there and then upload that again to
business Central and when you run the
report that's your template so it's
taking away the responsibility of the
layout experience out of the hands of
the developers and into the hands of
endusers so there are two things you can
ask yourself whenever you go into this
report if you see Excel here as we have
we do have reports of types Excel that's
great this means that this environment
here actually are using Excel layouts
great maybe you can do more you can do a
lot of things with Excel layouts you can
use power query to join data from
business Central with other data sources
tons of things you can do so any skilled
partner who knows about Excel or power
query powerbi could maybe do workshops
with you as a customer to do more with
Excel you're already paying for a
business Central license you're probably
paying for an office license with Excel
why not get more out of that um if
you're already using it and with all of
these the absence of data also tells you
something let's say that you don't see
any Excel here that actually means that
you as a customer or if you are a
partner this particular customer is
missing completely out on Excel layouts
missing out on all the self-service all
the things that end users could do
themselves um and that's a Pity in my
opinion I think that's a that's that's a
shame so data shows that they are using
it you can maybe do more um they here is
users absence of data is an opportunity
maybe to at least introduce this
capability and you as a customer can
decide no I'm fine we don't need this or
you can go hey I want this and I'm even
pay pay for it so I want it
now second thing I want to show you here
is connectors the connectors report show
Integrations into business Central from
teams Excel powerbi power automate power
apps power like all of
these and again you can use this to ask
questions about oh I can see this
particular environment is using a lot of
power automate great maybe we can do
work workshops together with as with
thect like the customer and the partner
to do more with with automate automate
more business
processes and again with absence of
power automate here there could be an
opportunity to to actually like digitize
business processes and do a lot uh
business Central is growing with power
automate and have more and more
capabilities of using power automate
together with business Central so there
could be opportunity to Simply go in and
digitize more business processes with
Automation and the last thing I want to
show in this part of the presentation is
application areas we talked a little bit
about it um when I when I showed you
this report earlier the fixed assets
report or or area here I mean most
companies do have fixed assets you have
bought things that maybe you should want
to track uh in your Earp system so this
could be an opportunity if there's no
usage of fixed assets maybe this is a
part of business Central where you're
already paying for it you could benefit
from this functionality tomorrow if you
start using it and train for it so as a
partner you could look for these maybe
lwh hanging fruits of business Central
functionality that the customer is not
using and help them get like more bang
for the buck and similarly if you from
the if you're from the customer end of
things if you're the project sponsor
maybe there are part of this um
application landscape where you you
think H there's something here called
fixed assets I don't know what it is but
I could look it up in the documentation
or ask my partner and maybe we could get
more value out of our licensing
money there are more examples of this if
you go to this URL here
aka.ms slbc - Telemetry D checklist it
takes you to a GitHub repository of lots
of things where I added um a PowerPoint
presentation it's meant for for partners
to do follow-ups with uh with customers
if you're on the customer end you could
just use this as maybe a way you would
like the follow-up customer meetings to
be with your partner and work together
use data to to get more value out of of
your
investment okay finally in this
presentation at least either is he not
done yet I want to get coffee or I want
this what should I
do well you need to do at least two
things but probably four the first thing
is you need to create what's called an
application insights resource in Asher
this is where we lock this data to it's
an Asher resource and you need to have a
way a place to lock this data so that's
the first thing I'll show you how second
you need to configure business Central
to actually lock Telemetry
there third you need to install the
powerbi apps that I have shown you here
it's optional but it's definitely
recommended without the powerbi content
you just have data but with the powerbi
content you actually have insights and
things you can take actions on
and then four you should set up alerts
on some key events in Telemetry it's
optional but definitely recommended you
can either use this approach I showed
you here with powerbi metrics or you can
also have use different tools that uh
that you can ask your partners or or you
can look at documentation of how to set
this
up Telemetry works both for online and
on premises environments so what
whatever
how you're hosted doesn't matter it
works both places we introduced this in
version 15 which is a few releases ago
we are releasing version 22 here in
April 2023 so the the later you are on a
version like the the higher version the
more data more types of data you get but
it does work from all the way down to
version
15 this is just a screenshot from from
the Asher portal when whenever you
create one of these application insights
this purple icon you just create click
create and you can do this as a customer
or you can have your partner do it and
really depends who should own this
data then how to set up Telemetry in
business Central it is as simple as one
two three first you need to go into the
tenant admin Center and find your
environment
here then you need to click Define under
application insights and that would open
will open up a small dialogue where you
need to copy in the application insights
um connection string it's very important
that you don't do this during working
hours because this will do a glitch for
a few minutes it will restart your
environment so don't do it while people
are working in business Central just do
it out of of business
hours and uh that's it actually that was
only two right number three here here is
a confirmation business Central
Telemetry is now configured and business
Central will start emitting
data the powerbi app exists on uh
Microsoft app Source you can either
search for business Central usage
analytics and install it there or you
can go to this URL uh here aka.ms
forward
slbc Telemetry report that will take you
through the full installation of the
powerbi app when you have installed it
you need to specify where is data
located so so there's a small connect to
your data you specify your application
insights application ID where is data
stored and how many days of data do you
want the app to
have maybe a month maybe two weeks maybe
a single day depends totally on you the
app will refresh every night and get the
latest whatever sliding window you
choose so call to action and this is the
last part before we start the the live
Q&A when the actual event is uh is is
here so enable to limitary in your
environments ask your administrator or
partner to do
so and they install the powerbi app um
you can do it your it's maybe there's
some like authorization that that need
the powerbi app needs to be able to read
data so maybe your administrator is the
right one for that whoever sets up
Telemetry and owns Telemetry Source
could be you as customer or the partner
same thing goes for the powerbi app it
just needs to be installed by the same
organization that owns the telary
resource the beauty about both of these
is that the other part if customer owns
Telemetry and installs the powerbi app
the customer can share both read access
to Telemetry and read access to the
powerbi report and vice versa so there's
no it's just how you prefer it about who
installs and who owns these resources
the most important thing is that you as
a customer and you as a partner taking
care of your customers should use data
to take decision
on how to do more with less with
business Central and with that I say
thank you so much Dynamic con virtual
for having me here for the Microsoft
customer success day looking forward to
all your questions and have a great
conference thank
you